Inventory of the Governor and the Students Videotape Series, 1973-1974
Hoover Institution Archives
The Governor and the Students videotape series
1973-1974
84078
Hoover Institution Archives
1 manuscript box and 77 videotapes (27.4 linear feet)
Videotape cassettes and selected transcripts of broadcasts of a televised series of question-and-answer sessions with high school students conducted by Ronald Reagan as governor of California, relating to California state political issues. Produced by JRH and Associates, Inc.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1984.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Collections
Deaver & Hannaford records, Hoover Institution Archives
Historical Note
Ronald Reagan described The Governor and the Students this way:
"During my last two years in office we had a program in cooperation with the department of education. Each week a different high school class would come to the Capitol and I would field their questions (or try to) for one hour. The program was entirely unrehearsed. I would meet them only a few minutes before we actually started and, of course, had no preview of their questions.
"The hour was taped for television and made available for closed circuit classroom use in all of California's 1100-plus school districts. It was also played on the educational TV network." [Box 1; original source unidentified]
The program gave Reagan a way to connect with young people. Modeled on the press conference format, the idea for the show originated with Reagan aides Michael K. Deaver and Joseph R. Holmes. High school students were chosen over college students on the theory that they lived with their parents, had not been exposed to liberal college professors, and would therefore be more polite and less radical.
The shows were taped on a weekday after school, and the videotapes were distributed to TV stations in California to air at no cost. While most were public broadcast stations, it aired on a commercial station in Visalia because there was no public broadcast station in that area. The series was produced by JRH and Associates in Sacramento. The name Young People's Television (YPTV) is also associated with this program.
Source: John H. Fund, "Leave It to Deaver: 'Close Reagan Aide Dies.' I Remember Him from High School," Jewish World Review, 20 August 2007, http://www.jewishworldreview.com/cols/fund082007.php3.
Scope and Content of Collection
This collection consists of videotapes and selected transcripts of broadcasts of a televised series of question-and-answer sessions with high school students conducted by Ronald Reagan as governor of California, relating to California state political issues.
Transcripts are available for ten programs, and lists of questions asked by the students are available for another ten shows.
Labels on the videotapes provide limited information about their contents. Fully identifying each tape by date and version is dependent on, and limited by, its label. Some tapes are labeled as opening and closing credits sequences. Based on the videotape labels, it appears that the programs are about 30 minutes in duration.
JRH and Associates, Inc.; Reagan, Ronald.; California--Politics and government--1951-; Video tapes.
- Lists and transcripts, 1973-1974
  Scope and Contents note
  Lists of questions asked, and transcripts of entire programs, arranged by physical form.
  - General papers, undated (Box-folder 1: 1)
    Account by Reagan and public broadcast schedule for 1973-74 season
  - Lists of questions or topics, 1973-1974 (Box-folder 1: 2)
    - Loretto High School, 14 May 1974 (Box-folder 1: 2)
    - Rio Vista High School, 18 March 1974 (Box-folder 1: 2)
    - Pleasant Hill High School, 13 March 1974 (Box-folder 1: 2)
    - Stockton Unified School District, 26 February 1974 (Box-folder 1: 2)
    - Sacramento High School, 4 February 1974 (Box-folder 1: 2)
    - Oak Grove High School (San Jose) and Encina High School (Sacramento), 7 January 1974 (Box-folder 1: 2)
    - Delta High School, 14 January 1974 (Box-folder 1: 2)
    - San Diego, 25 October 1973 (Box-folder 1: 2)
    - Orange County Schools, 16 October 1973 (Box-folder 1: 2)
    - Durham High and Chico Senior High, 3 October 1973 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Transcripts, 1973 (Box-folder 1: 3)
    - Eighth graders, 7 February 1973 (Box-folder 1: 3)
    - Rocklin School, 8 March 1973 (Box-folder 1: 3)
    - Sutter Junior High, 22 March 1973 (Box-folder 1: 3)
    - El Camino High School, 12 April 1973 (Box-folder 1: 4)
    - Rio Americano High School, 26 April 1973 (Box-folder 1: 4)
    - Luther Burbank High School, 5 May 1973 (Box-folder 1: 4)
    - Summer school students, Sacramento area, 18 June 1973 (Box-folder 1: 4)
    - Boy's State, 21 June 1973 (Box-folder 1: 5)
    - San Jose School District, 17 September 1973 (Box-folder 1: 5)
    - Rio Americano, 24 September 1973 (Box-folder 1: 5)
- Videorecordings, 1973-1974
  Videotapes of entire programs and of opening and closing credits sequences. Arranged by videotape format in three groups: one-inch videoreels, two-inch videoreels, and U-matic videocassette.
  - One-inch videoreels, 1973-1974 (Tape 1-26)
    - The Governor and the Students: Modesto City Schools, 29 January 1973 (Tape 1)
      Members of Modesto City Schools' Inter-High Student Council ask Governor Ronald Reagan questions in the room where Reagan holds press conferences.
      Sequence: This program has no clear-cut beginning and end. Content begins with Reagan's voice chatting off-air (00:26), visuals begin with view of students (00:35), and Reagan begins formal remarks (00:45) followed by a superimposed program title (00:50). First question, on capital punishment (02:20), last question, about abortion, is partially lost due to dropout (29:18), but picks up again (29:31). Reagan indicates program is over (30:35), but takes another question, but footage ends abruptly before he replies.
      There are 30 seconds of color bars at beginning, then audio comes in before video. Color shift, jumpy images, and dropout due to deterioration of original tape. Image and sound dropout from 00:29:18 - 00:29:32. Additional Title: Inter-High Student Council, 29 January 1973.
    - The Governor and the Students: Pleasant Ridge Elementary School, February 7, 1973; The Governor's News Conference, 7 February 1973 (Tape 2)
      In the first program, students at Pleasant Ridge Elementary School ask Governor Ronald Reagan questions in press conference format. An extended segment in the middle of the videotape presents part of another student press conference with Reagan. In the second program, Governor Ronald Reagan fields questions at a press conference whose date is not indicated.
      Sequence: PART 1, The Governor and the Students: Fade in to Reagan getting started with the students (01:03), program title is superimposed over image (01:12), first question, about education as a priority issue (01:19), closing credits for a different program, The Governor's Press Conference (28:40). PART 2, The Governor and the Students: Fade in to Reagan answering a question about the cost of the California governor's mansion (29:25), closing credits superimposed over post-taping activity including technician removing microphone from Reagan, Reagan chatting with students (36:11). PART 3, The Governor's News Conference: Opening sequence (38:27), empty podium, reporters chatting (38:53), Reagan walks to podium, begins speaking (39:18), first question, about the new study of the capitol reporting that it requires about $41 million to rebuild (39:43), closing credits (1:02:17).
      Color shift, jumpy images, and dropout due to deterioration of original tape.
    - The Governor and the Students: Rocklin Elementary School, 9 March 1973 (Tape 3)
      Eighth graders from Rocklin ask Governor Ronald Reagan questions.
      Sequence: Opening title sequence begins (00:47), program opens with Reagan's introduction (01:14), first question (01:33), program ends in mid-sentence (59:35).
      Slate indicates 8-23-73 as recording date. Note on original container: "Recorded 3/8/73. First half hour shown 3/9/73."
    - 29 March 1973 (?) (Tape 4)
    - The Governor's Press Conference, 17 August 1973 (Tape 5)
      This is a press conference held by Governor Ronald Reagan at the state capitol in Sacramento. Produced by JRH and Associates, Inc.
      Sequence: Slate (01:11), opening sequence (01:24), Reagan walks to podium and begins speaking (01:37), first question, regarding Watergate (01:54), last question, about budget negotiations (28:32), closing sequence (28:56). The program is followed by a short remnant taped at a different press conference, with comments about a budget surplus (29:43) followed by closing credits (30:26).
      Color shift, jumpy images, and dropout due to deterioration of original tape. Audio is muffled in last couple minutes. There is an additional minute or so of content after the credits.
    - The Governor and the Students: Hiram Johnson High School (part 1), 14 May 1973 (Tape 6)
      Juniors from Hiram Johnson High School, Sacramento, ask Governor Ronald Reagan questions in press conference format.
      Sequence: Part 1: Slate (00:57), opening sequence (01:15), Reagan introduces program (01:28), first question, concerning whether Reagan views Joseph Alioto, mayor of San Francisco, as a major threat to Republican fortunes, closing credits (29:14).
      Color shift, jumpy images, and dropout due to deterioration of original tapes. Part 2 is on tape 7.
    - The Governor and the Students: Hiram Johnson High School (part 2)(10), 14 May 1973 (Tape 7)
      Sequence: Part 2: Slate (00:22), opening sequence (00:38), Reagan introduces program (00:53), first question, about whether Reagan will ever go back to show business (01:15), closing credits (28:39).
      Color shift, jumpy images, and dropout due to deterioration of original tapes.
      This item is available for viewing as part of Part 1.
    - The Governor and the Students: Luther Burbank High School (11, 12), 22 May 1973 (Tape 8)
      Juniors and seniors chosen from a variety of subject-matter classes at Luther Burbank High School ask Governor Ronald Reagan questions.
      Sequence: PART 1: Opening slate (00:23), opening sequence (00:43), Reagan begins introduction (00:57), first question, about bombing in Cambodia (01:28), last question, about prison as punishment or rehabilitation (27:06), abrupt cut off in mid-sentence and closing credits (29:05). PART 2: Opening slate (30:36), opening sequence (30:55), Reagan begins speaking (31:09), first question, about guaranteed annual income (31:23), last question, about protection and public access to California's coast (58:12), fade-out in mid-sentence and closing sequence (59:11).
      Color shift, jumpy images, and dropout due to deterioration of original tape. The videotape label and slate for part 2 indicate that the program was taped on May 22, 1973, but the slate for part 1 provides a date of 9-7-73. This program appears to be the same as the program on tapes 69 and 73.
    - The Governor and the Students: College of Marin (13, 14), 11 June 1973 (Tape 9)
      Freshman and sophomores from the College of Marin ask Governor Ronald Reagan questions in press conference format.
      Sequence: PART 1: Slate (00:47), opening sequence with sound preceding image (01:01), Reagan introduces program (01:25), student corrects Reagan's mistake in name of college and then asks first question, about how much control the state should have over education, especially at community colleges (02:12), closing credits (27:31). PART 2: Slate (29:48), opening sequence (30:07), program begins as student is asking question about California state government's investments in South Africa (30:20), closing credits (59:06).
      Color shift, jumpy images, and dropout due to deterioration of original tape. The dates of these programs are somewhat uncertain. The slate for the first indicates the date as 6/11, while the slate for the second indicates the date as 1-2-74. The second program on this tape appears to be the same content as that on tape 38, though the format of the opening sequence and closing credits differ.
    - The Governor and the Students: High Schools in San Jose, 17 September 1973 (Tape 10)
      Seniors from five high schools in San Jose ask Governor Reagan questions in press conference format.
      Sequence: PART 1: Slate (01:01), opening sequence (01:21), Reagan introduces program (01:34), first question, about how Californians will benefit from the tax and expenditure limitation initiative (02:29), closing sequence (29:16). PART 2: Slate (31:00), opening sequence (31:24), Reagan introduces program (31:36), first question, about agricultural land planning in the context of California's population growth (31:54), closing credits superimposed over footage of Reagan and students (59:01).
      Color shift, jumpy images, and dropout due to deterioration of original tape. The date of these programs is not clear. The slate for the first show indicates the date as 9/17, while the slate for the second show indicates the date as 9/27/73.
    - The Governor and the Students: Rio Americano High School, 24 September 1973 (Tape 11)
      Seniors from Rio Americano High School in Sacramento ask Governor Ronald Reagan questions in an unedited, unrehearsed format resembling a press conference.
      Sequence: PART 1: Slate (01:20), opening sequence (01:39), Reagan introduces the program (01:53), first question is asked, about Reagan's secret to success as governor and as a possible presidential candidate (02:24), closing credits (28:53). PART 2: Opening sequence (30:40), Reagan introduces the program (30:57), first question, about purchasing a jet airplane after Reagan had stressed budget discipline (31:16), closing credits (58:19).
    - GPS Master, 30 September 1973 (Tape 12)
    - The Governor and the Students: Durham and Chico Senior High Schools, 3 October 1973 (Tape 13)
      Students from two high schools in Butte County, Durham and Chico Senior High Schools, ask Governor Ronald Reagan questions in press conference format.
      Sequence: PART 1: Slate (01:21), opening sequence (02:53), Reagan introduces the program (03:08), first question, about the energy crisis and whether California will have the same problems that Oregon has experienced (03:31), closing credits (30:17). PART 2: Slate (33:00), opening sequence (33:20), Reagan introduces the program (33:39), first question, about what was done with the money from the federal milk reimbursement program (34:02), closing credits (1:01:24).
      Jumpy images, and dropout due to deterioration of original tape. Audio levels are low.The tape also has remnants of earlier episodes of this television series, indicating that the tape was reused. The date these two programs were taped is not clear. They appear to be taped on the same day, but the slate for part 1 has the date 10/3 while the slate for part 2 has the date 11/8/73.
    - Encina-Oak Grove, #17 A and B, time: 28:30 and 28:30, January 1974 (Tape 14)
    - #18 A and B, Delta, time: 28:10 and 28:25, 14 January 1974 (Tape 15)
    - Sacramento High School, #19 A and B, time: 27:30 and 27:30, 13 February 1974 (Tape 16)
    - Pleasant Hill, 1st and 2nd half, 27 March 1974 (Tape 17)
    - Loretto High School, time: 28:30 and 28:25, 14 May 1974 (Tape 18)
    - Face the Students (Joe Holmes), show #6A and 6B, time: 27:10 and 27:30, 13 November 1974 (Tape 19)
    - Holmes-Land, undated (Tape 20)
    - Holmes-Land, undated (Tape 21)
    - Untitled, undated (Tape 22)
    - Untitled, undated (Tape 23)
    - For GPC, Department of Motor Vehicles, undated (Tape 24 (#6))
    - Senator A. Alquist, Report, time: 11:07, undated (Tape 25)
    - #15 and 16, McClatchy, undated (Tape 26)
  - Two-inch videoreels, 1973-1974 (Tape 27-76)
    - Joe Holmes (on the cover), time: 3:00, 19 April 1973 (Tape 27)
    - Press Conference (Show #7), Master, time: 28:00, 26 April 1973 (Tape 28 (17))
    - Show #8, 26 April 1973 (Tape 29)
    - The Governor and the Students: High Schools in San Jose, 7 September 1973 (Tape 30)
      Sequence: Slate (00:29), opening sequence (00:46), Reagan introduces program (01:01), first question, about how Californians will benefit from the tax and expenditure limitation initiative (01:56), closing credits (28:43).
      This program is a duplicate of the first program of The Governor and the Students: High Schools in San Jose (tape 10). Alternate Title: The Governor and the Students [San Jose, time: 28:36, 7 September 1973].
    - Chico, time: A-27:05, B-27:40, 3 October 1973 (Tape 31 (12))
    - The Governor and the Students: Rio Americano High School, 24 September 1973 (Tape 32 (11))
    - The Governor and the Students: Opening sequence, 29 October 1973 (Tape 33)
      This is one of the opening title sequences used for "The Governor and the Students."
      Sequence data: Slate appears (00:53), opening title sequence begins (01:05), sequence ends (01:36)
    - 28 November 1973, time: 28:20 (Tape 34)
    - Holmes-Land, College of Marin (A), time: 26:50, 19 December 1973 (Tape 35 (21))
    - The Governor and the Students: Jesuit High School, 19 December 1973 (Tape 36 (32))
      This program features a group of honorary scholastic students at Jesuit High School in Sacramento. It was taped on location in one of the studios of Channel 10. A public safety announcement (PSA) about seat belts precedes the main program. Governor Reagan drives up to a sheriff who is standing along the road and talks to him through the car window. The sheriff thanks Reagan for wearing his seat belt. Reagan tells the sheriff how seat belts save lives, then turns to the camera and says, "Why don't you belt yourself." The sheriff turns to the camera and suggests that you "belt your wife or girlfriend--keep her alive too."
      Sequence: seat belt PSA (00:23), opening title sequence (01:18), Reagan begins speaking (01:40), first question, about public aid to private schools (02:15), closing sequence (28:18).
      Labels on the tape indicated that this tape concerned the College of Marin, 19 December 1973. While there is no introductory slate, Reagan's introduction details it to be Jesuit High. There is no confirmation of the date on the label.
    - The Governor and the Students: Encina and Oak Grove High Schools (17A, 17B), 9 January 1974 (Tape 37 (25))
      This program features a combination of seniors from two schools, Oak Grove High School in San Jose and Encina High School in Sacramento.
      Sequence: PART 1: Visual of Reagan talking to students, but no sound (00:00), black (01:06), introductory slate (01:12), opening title sequence (01:42), Reagan begins speaking (02:03), first question, about Watergate (02:37), closing sequence (28:42). PART 2: introductory slate (01:17), opening title sequence (01:38), Reagan begins speaking (02:00), first question, about oil drilling around Santa Barbara and the environment (02:23), closing sequence (28:44).
      Two videotapes represent two different programs taped at the same location on the same day, identified on the slate as programs 17A and 17B, taped January 7. Labels on the tapes are January 9 and January 16, 1974, which may be the broadcast dates.
    - The Governor and the Students: College of Marin? (part 2), 9 January 1974 (Tape 38)
      This program features an unidentified group of students. It appears to have been taped in the studio at the state capitol. Tape labelling indicates this as College of Marin, but the introductory slate indicates only that it is the Governor and Students 6/11 number 14. Because the program cuts off some amount of the beginning, Reagan's introduction, during which he identifies the students to the audience, is missing. While the tape label lists the date as 9 January 1974, the slate suggests it is June 11.
      Sequence: introductory slate (00:33), McGraw-Hill Pacific Productions slate (01:27), opening title sequence (01:38), program begins in the middle of a student asking Reagan a question (01:58), closing sequence (30:31).
      To view the streaming video, see the link at Jesuit High School.
    - Delta 18B, time: 28:28, 14 January 1974 (Tape 39)
    - The Governor and the Students: Encina and Oak Grove, 16 January 1974 (Tape 40 (17B))
      See program 17A for a description and link to the streaming video.
    - The Governor and the Students: Delta High School (18-A, 18-B), 14 January 1974 (Tape 41 (4))
      Juniors and seniors in a civics class at Delta High School ask Governor Ronald Reagan questions in press conference format.
      Sequence: PART 1: Slate (00:50), opening sequence (01:13), Reagan introduces as second of two programs with Delta H.S. (01:34), first question, about the smoking bill and student smoking on campus (01:49), closing credits (29:17). PART 2: Slate (01:07), opening sequence (01:29), Reagan introduces program (01:50), first question, about the US Supreme Court decision concerning search and seizure (02:33), closing credits (29:03).
      Alternate Titles: Part 1: The Governor and the Students [Delta 18B, time 28:28, 14 January 1974]; Part 2: The Governor and the Students [Delta High School, 18-A, 23 January 1974]
    - The Governor and the Students: Sacramento High School (part 1), 4 February 1974 (Tape 42 (3))
      This program features juniors and seniors at Sacramento High School in Sacramento. Two videotapes represent two different programs taped at the same location on the same day, identified on the slate as programs 19A and 19B, taped February 4. The label on the tape lists the date as February 4, 1974.
      Sequence: PROGRAM 19A: introductory slate (01:13), opening title sequence (01:33), Reagan begins speaking (01:54), first question, about banning visitors to the state capitol due to seismic safety concerns (02:10), closing sequence (29:15). PROGRAM 19B: introductory slate (01:23), opening title sequence (01:44), Reagan begins speaking (02:05), first question, about Reagan's future political aspirations (02:18), closing sequence (29:34).
    - The Governor and the Students: Sacramento High School (part 2), 4 February 1974 (Tape 43 (7))
      See the previous program for a description and link to the streaming video.
    - The Governor and the Students: Mark Keppel High School, 8 February 1974 (Tape 44 (9))
      Students from three government classes at Mark Keppel High School in Alhambra ask Governor Ronald Reagan questions in press conference format. This program was taped in Los Angeles.
      Sequence: Opening sequence (00:43), Reagan introduces program (01:04), first question, about the ignorance and apathy of students regarding world affairs (01:30), closing credits (28:11).
      Alternate Title: The Governor and the Students [Mark Keppel School, A Master, time: 27:52, 8 February 1974]
    - The Governor and the Students: Stockton Unified School District, 26 February 1974 (Tape 45 (1))